<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-06-05T15:49:07+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Joel Salazar</title><subtitle>IT Consulting &amp; Management Services</subtitle><entry><title type="html">A Closer Look to America’s Labor Shortage</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/marketing/a-closer-look-to-americas-labor-shortage/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Closer Look to America’s Labor Shortage" /><published>2024-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/marketing/a-closer-look-to-americas-labor-shortage</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/marketing/a-closer-look-to-americas-labor-shortage/"><![CDATA[<p>The most recent data from the US Chamber of Commerce and the Bureau of Labor Statistics shows that by April 2024, there were 8.5 million job openings in the U.S. national market but only 6.5 million unemployed workers available to fill them. This disparity highlights a crucial challenge: a labor shortage with far-reaching implications for the economy and various industries.
<!--more--></p>

<p><img src="https://h7g4rb6t8u7i.blob.core.windows.net/blog/w7yg62er9p13.svg" alt="US NATIONAL MARKET CHART" /></p>

<p>Despite employers adding 3.1 million jobs in 2023, the labor force participation rate has not rebounded to pre-pandemic levels. <strong>In April 2024, the labor force participation rate was 62.7%, down from 63.3% in February 2020 and significantly lower than the 67.2% recorded in January 2001.</strong></p>

<p>Most states have more job openings now than before the pandemic, as shown by the Worker Shortage Index, a ratio that indicates the number of available workers for each job opening. As of April 2024, <strong>significant worker shortages are affecting several states, with North Dakota at the top of the list.</strong></p>

<p><img src="https://h7g4rb6t8u7i.blob.core.windows.net/blog/9fet481193wg.png" alt="WORKER SHORTAGE INDEX CHART" /></p>

<h2 id="current-work-arrangements">Current Work Arrangements</h2>
<p>Data sourced from ITAM, Stanford University, and the University of Chicago in 2023 provide a clear snapshot of how different industries have adapted to the new normal. Their analysis categorizes work arrangements into three types: fully on-site, hybrid (a mix of on-site and remote work), and fully remote.</p>

<p><img src="https://h7g4rb6t8u7i.blob.core.windows.net/blog/x7ufsu4ht16g.png" alt="US WORK ARRANGEMENTS CHART" /></p>

<p>The highest propensity for in-person work still exists in industries like hospitality and food services, where nearly 80% of staff work fully on-site. Alternatively, <strong>industries with a low amount of physical labor are more likely to work remotely, such as information or professional services, where less than 45% of staff are fully on-site.</strong></p>

<h2 id="industry-insights">Industry Insights</h2>

<h3 id="leisure-and-hospitality-industry">Leisure and Hospitality Industry</h3>
<p>Since November 2020, the leisure and hospitality industry has maintained the highest hiring rate among all industries, ranging from 6% to nearly 19%. This hiring rate remains significantly higher than the national average, which has hovered around 3.7% since January 2024. However, there is still a gap, with <strong>1,153 thousand job openings in April 2024 but only 784 thousand unemployed workers.</strong></p>

<p><img src="https://h7g4rb6t8u7i.blob.core.windows.net/blog/1wh2t9fugtxt.svg" alt="US HOSPITALITY INDUSTRY CHART" /></p>

<h3 id="professional-services-industry">Professional Services Industry</h3>
<p>The professional services industry, encompassing fields such as consulting and advertising, has also been impacted by the labor shortage. The shift to remote work has offered some flexibility, but the need for specialized skills and experience remains a critical issue, with <strong>1,485 thousand job openings in April 2024 but only 7 thousand unemployed workers.</strong></p>

<p><img src="https://h7g4rb6t8u7i.blob.core.windows.net/blog/dgbsqb332u94.svg" alt="US PROFESSIONAL SERVICES INDUSTRY CHART" /></p>

<h3 id="information-industry">Information Industry</h3>
<p>The information industry has seen a surge in demand due to the increased need for remote work and digital services. However, the rapid pace of innovation has outstripped the supply of skilled workers, contributing to the labor shortage, with <strong>169 thousand job openings in April 2024 but only 128 thousand unemployed workers.</strong></p>

<p><img src="https://h7g4rb6t8u7i.blob.core.windows.net/blog/3ub5193eymeq.svg" alt="US INFORMATION INDUSTRY CHART" /></p>

<h2 id="looking-ahead">Looking ahead</h2>
<p>The projected changes in employment from 2022 to 2032 provide insight into the shifting landscape of America’s job market. Key trends and implications include significant growth in sectors such as <strong>computer and mathematical, with a projected growth of 15.2%, fueled by continuous technological advancements</strong> and the growing reliance on digital infrastructure and data analysis.</p>

<p>Industries facing decline include <strong>office and administrative support, anticipated to decrease by 6.2%, largely due to automation</strong> and digitization reducing the need for traditional administrative roles. However, automation may also create new jobs in areas such as design, engineering, and maintenance of these technologies.</p>

<p><img src="https://h7g4rb6t8u7i.blob.core.windows.net/blog/sbi194jr2f66.png" alt="US EMPLOYMENT PROJECTIONS CHART" /></p>

<h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2>
<p>In conclusion, the labor shortage revealed by recent data from the US Chamber of Commerce and the Bureau of Labor Statistics poses a significant challenge for the U.S. economy and various industries. Despite the addition of 3.1 million jobs in 2023, the labor force participation rate has yet to return to pre-pandemic levels, highlighting the complexity of the current employment landscape. Moreover, while many states have experienced an increase in job openings compared to pre-pandemic levels, the disparity between job openings and available workers remains a pressing issue, with states like North Dakota facing significant worker shortages.</p>

<p>As we delve deeper into the dynamics of different industries, it becomes evident that the nature of work arrangements has shifted in response to the pandemic. While some sectors, such as leisure and hospitality, continue to rely heavily on in-person work, others, like the professional services and information industries, have embraced remote work to adapt to changing circumstances. However, the challenges posed by the labor shortage persist across industries, emphasizing the need for innovative solutions and strategies to address the evolving demands of the modern workforce. Looking ahead, projections for employment trends from 2022 to 2032 underscore the importance of adapting to technological advancements and preparing for the changing nature of work in the digital age.</p>

<h3 id="sources">Sources</h3>

<div class="slinks">

  <p><a href="https://www.uschamber.com/workforce/understanding-americas-labor-shortage">Ferguson, S. (2024). Understanding America’s Labor Shortage. US Chamber of Commerce.</a>
<a href="https://www.uschamber.com/workforce/the-states-suffering-most-from-the-labor-shortage">Cates, L., &amp; Ferguson, S. (2024). Understanding America’s Labor Shortage: The Most Impacted States.</a>
<a href="https://www.uschamber.com/workforce/data-deep-dive-the-workforce-of-the-future">Lucy, I., Shrove, J., &amp; Ferguson, S. (2023). Data Deep Dive: The Workforce of the Future.</a></p>

</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="marketing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The most recent data from the US Chamber of Commerce and the Bureau of Labor Statistics shows that by April 2024, there were 8.5 million job openings in the U.S. national market but only 6.5 million unemployed workers available to fill them. This disparity highlights a crucial challenge: a labor shortage with far-reaching implications for the economy and various industries.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2024 Key Market Indicators</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/marketing/2024-key-market-indicators/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2024 Key Market Indicators" /><published>2024-05-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/marketing/2024-key-market-indicators</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/marketing/2024-key-market-indicators/"><![CDATA[<p>The recent economic data for the United States reveals a nuanced picture of the nation’s economic trajectory, highlighting both areas of growth and emerging challenges. Let’s break down the key insights and their implications for business owners and policymakers.
<!--more--></p>

<h2 id="gdp-growth-rate">GDP Growth Rate</h2>
<p>In the dynamic landscape of economics, the Gross Domestic Product (GDP) serves as a vital barometer, reflecting the overall health and performance of a country’s economy. With the release of the first estimate for the first quarter of 2024, business owners eagerly awaited insights into the trajectory of the United States’ economic growth. Let’s delve into the recent data and its implications.</p>

<p><strong>The forecasted GDP growth rate for the second quarter of 2024 stands at 1.5%</strong>, indicating a slowdown from the previous quarter’s 2.4%. This deceleration suggests that while the economy is still expanding, the pace of growth is slowing. For business owners, this may signal a need for cautious optimism, focusing on maintaining stability and efficiency rather than aggressive expansion.</p>

<p><img src="https://h7g4rb6t8u7i.blob.core.windows.net/blog/3531pu9bfa85.svg" alt="US GDP GROWTH RATE CHART" /></p>

<h2 id="key-market-indicators">Key Market Indicators</h2>

<h3 id="inflation-rate">Inflation Rate</h3>
<p><strong>The US inflation rate is currently at 3.36%</strong>, a slight decrease from 3.48% last month and significantly lower than 4.93% a year ago. However, it remains above the long-term average of 3.28%.</p>

<h3 id="real-estate-market">Real Estate Market</h3>
<p><strong>The price per square foot in April was $230</strong>, up 3.6% from $222 in April of last year. The increase in real estate prices may reflect ongoing demand and potential constraints in supply.</p>

<h3 id="housing-market">Housing Market</h3>
<p><strong>The US median asking rent has risen to $1,459</strong>, a significant 11.63% increase from $1,307 one year ago. The sharp rise in rental costs can affect consumer patterns, as higher housing costs reduce disposable income.</p>

<h3 id="automotive-market">Automotive Market</h3>
<p><strong>The average price for a new car in March was $47,218</strong>, a decrease of 1% from March 2023 and a 5.4% drop from the market peak in December 2022. The decline in car prices suggests a cooling off in the automotive market, potentially due to changes in consumer demand.</p>

<h3 id="insurance-costs">Insurance Costs</h3>
<p><strong>The national average cost of car insurance is $2,004 per year for full coverage</strong> and $624 per year for minimum coverage. The costs of insurance are significant for both individuals and businesses, affecting overall operating expenses and consumer spending power.</p>

<h3 id="retail-gas-prices">Retail Gas Prices</h3>
<p><strong>The US retail gas price is at a current level of $3.698</strong>, down from $3.706 last week and up from $3.645 one year ago. Fluctuating gas prices can influence transportation costs and labor shortages.</p>

<h2 id="looking-ahead">Looking Ahead</h2>
<p>As we progress through 2024, the economic landscape presents several challenges and opportunities. With GDP growth slowing to 1.5% in the second quarter, businesses should prioritize efficiency and stability. Inflation remains above the long-term average, making cost control essential. Rising real estate and rent prices could impact expansion plans and consumer spending, while lower car prices reflect shifting demand in the automotive market. High insurance expenses continue to be a significant cost, and fluctuating gas prices will affect transportation costs. As a business owner, staying informed and adaptable will be crucial for navigating these economic shifts effectively.</p>

<h3 id="sources">Sources</h3>

<div class="slinks">

  <p><a href="https://www.bea.gov/data/gdp/gross-domestic-product">U.S. Bureau of Economic Analysis. (n.d.). Gross Domestic Product.</a>
<a href="https://www.ey.com/en_us/insights/strategy/macroeconomics/us-gdp-q1-2024-first-estimate">EY. (2024). US GDP Q1 2024 First Estimate.</a>
<a href="https://www.nerdwallet.com/article/finance/gdp-report">NerdWallet (2024). GDP report: Economy grew by 1.6% in the first quarter of 2024.</a>
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LNuGCEcjcgg">STR. (2024). Economic growth slowdown expected in 2024.</a>
<a href="https://ycharts.com/indicators/us_inflation_rate#:~:text=US%20Inflation%20Rate%20is%20at,in%20price%20over%20a%20year">YCharts. (2024). Overview of US Inflation Rate.</a>
<a href="https://fred.stlouisfed.org/series/MEDLISPRIPERSQUFEEUS">Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis. (2024). Median Listing Price per Square Feet in the United States.</a>
<a href="https://www.kbb.com/car-news/new-car-prices-lowest-in-almost-2-years/#:~:text=The%20average%20new%20car%20buyer,market%20peak%20in%20December%202022.">Kelley Blue Book. (2024). New Car Prices Lowest in Almost 2 Years.</a>
<a href="https://ycharts.com/indicators/us_gas_price">YCharts. (2024). US Retail Gas Price.</a>
<a href="https://www.marketwatch.com/guides/insurance-services/average-cost-of-car-insurance/">MarketWatch. (2024). Average Car Insurance Cost.</a>
<a href="https://ycharts.com/indicators/us_median_asking_rent_yearly">YCharts. (2024). US Median Asking Rent.</a></p>

</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="marketing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The recent economic data for the United States reveals a nuanced picture of the nation’s economic trajectory, highlighting both areas of growth and emerging challenges. Let’s break down the key insights and their implications for business owners and policymakers.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Build a Jekyll blog using Docker</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coding/build-a-jekyll-blog-using-docker/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Build a Jekyll blog using Docker" /><published>2024-03-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/coding/build-a-jekyll-blog-using-docker</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coding/build-a-jekyll-blog-using-docker/"><![CDATA[<p>Unleash the power of Docker for a hassle-free Jekyll blog setup and deployment. This technical guide will cover the essentials of using Docker containers to streamline your development workflow, ensuring a smooth transition from local development to live publication. Let’s get started! 🚀
<!--more--></p>

<p>First, let’s create a “dockerfile” with the necessary instructions to build our image.</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-docker" data-lang="docker">  <span class="c"># Dockerfile for Jekyll using Ubuntu</span>
  FROM ubuntu:latest
  <span class="c"># Install necessary packages</span>
  RUN apt-get update &amp;&amp; \
      apt-get install -y ruby-full build-essential zlib1g-dev git &amp;&amp; \
      git config --global init.defaultBranch main
  <span class="c"># Install Jekyll and Bundler</span>
  RUN gem install bundler jekyll
  <span class="c"># Set the working directory inside the container</span>
  WORKDIR /srv/jekyll</code></pre></figure>

<p>Proceed to build the image “jekyll-ubuntu” using the command <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&gt; docker build -t jekyll-ubuntu .</code></p>

<p>Run a container, mount the volume “ghpages”, and execute a “bash” terminal using this command</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-docker" data-lang="docker">  &gt; docker run --rm -it -p 4000:4000 -p 35729:35729 -v ghpages:/srv/jekyll jekyll-ubuntu bash</code></pre></figure>

<p>Create a new jekyll site, then launch the local server</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell">  <span class="nv">$ </span>jekyll new <span class="nb">.</span>
  <span class="nv">$ </span>bundle <span class="nb">exec </span>jekyll serve <span class="nt">--host</span> 0.0.0.0 <span class="nt">--livereload</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>If you already have an existing volume with a jekyll site, use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">bundle install</code> instead of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">jekyll new .</code> then launch the server</p>

<p>Finally, simply connect to the container via Visual Studio Code and designate “/srv/jekyll” as your workspace to begin crafting your Jekyll blog.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="coding" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Unleash the power of Docker for a hassle-free Jekyll blog setup and deployment. This technical guide will cover the essentials of using Docker containers to streamline your development workflow, ensuring a smooth transition from local development to live publication. Let’s get started! 🚀]]></summary></entry></feed>